<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Louis Simoneau]]></title>
  <link href="http://lsimoneau.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lsimoneau.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-09T08:34:46+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://lsimoneau.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Simoneau]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's the worst mistake I'm empowered to make?]]></title>
    <link href="http://lsimoneau.github.io/2013/10/25/whats-the-worst-mistake-im-empowered-to-make/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T21:39:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://lsimoneau.github.io/2013/10/25/whats-the-worst-mistake-im-empowered-to-make</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago a coworker of mine ordered a glass of beer in a pub while waiting for some pizzas to bring back to the office. After taking a big gulp, he immediately felt a burning sensation in his mouth and throat, and knew something was wrong. It turned out that the pub had recently cleaned the beer tap lines with a potent cleaning fluid, and it hadn&rsquo;t all been flushed out. The result was that my friend spent a night in the hospital, and was unable to eat anything for over a day due to the swelling and pain in his throat. It&rsquo;s still not totally clear what his path to recovery will be like.</p>

<p>When I told the story to another friend, his reaction was &ldquo;Wow. It&rsquo;s almost like, as a barman, what&rsquo;s the worst mistake I&rsquo;m empowered to make?&rdquo; And it&rsquo;s true. Quite literally, there&rsquo;s not a thing you can do in the execution of a bartender&rsquo;s job that is worse than serving a customer highly caustic cleaning fluid in their drink.</p>

<p>And that got me thinking. What&rsquo;s the worst mistake <em>I&rsquo;m</em> empowered to make? Take the site down? Nope, pretty easy to have it back up in a few minutes, little harm done. Commit a bug to production? It would have to be a whopper. Really, the worst thing I think I&rsquo;m empowered to do is lose data. If I break something such that, even if we recover, we&rsquo;ve lost some user data, that&rsquo;s deadly. I can&rsquo;t think of any other single misstep that would be more damaging to the company.</p>

<p>As soon as I came up with that answer, I realized I actually spend quite a lot of time thinking about it. Ever since the first time I shelled in to a production server, and not infrequently since, this little voice at the back of my head asks: <em>Are you about to hose any data?</em> Every time I&rsquo;m running complex migrations, or implement a new feature that alters data in a major why, it&rsquo;s always there: <em>Don&rsquo;t do the wost thing you could possibly do.</em></p>

<p>Let me be clear: avoiding catastrophic fuckups isn&rsquo;t what I consider the hallmark of a great software developer, or a great anything for that matter. To be <em>great</em>, you need to succeed greatly, not simply avoid failure. But coming back to the example of the pub: this was a <em>really good</em> pub. Fantastic selection of craft beers, best pizzas in the area by a wide margin, and a very welcoming atmosphere. But I still won&rsquo;t be going back there, because, well, obviously: they poisonned a friend of mine.</p>

<p>So it&rsquo;s probably worth spending a little bit of time, every once in awhile, asking yourself what the worst possible mistake you&rsquo;re empowered to make is. And putting in place whatever safeguards seem reasonable to stop yourself from making it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
